<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Labs on A minimal Hugo website</title>
    <link>/lab/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Labs on A minimal Hugo website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/lab/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A First Look at Ethics in Computer and Data Sciences</title>
      <link>/lab/a-first-look-at-ethics-in-computer-and-data-sciences/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/a-first-look-at-ethics-in-computer-and-data-sciences/</guid>
      <description>A First Look at Ethics in Computer and Data Sciences
Module Summary
 Ethics background required: None
Subject matter referred to in this module: computer and data science tasks
Placement in overall ethics curriculum:
 Academic year: First year, first semester, probably introductory programming course
 Recommended previous modules: Why Ethics?
 Recommended follow-up modules: Virtue Ethics* *
Time required:
 In class: 25 minutes
Learning objectives:
  Students are introduced to the 3 ethical frameworks that are</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analogies: Coding-Writing Plagiarism Example</title>
      <link>/lab/analogies-module-code-plagiarism-/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/analogies-module-code-plagiarism-/</guid>
      <description>Analogies: Coding-Writing Plagiarism Example
Module Summary
 Ethics background required: Knowledge of three primary frameworks is helpful, but is briefly presented
 Subject matter referred to in this module: Computer programming
 Placement in overall ethics curriculum:
 Academic year: First year, second semester, programming course
 Recommended previous modules: Why ethics? Any of the first year modules
 Recommended follow-up modules: Utilitarianism module (if not already seen) or any content modules.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Avoiding Algorithmic Bias Module</title>
      <link>/lab/avoiding-algorithmic-bias-module/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/avoiding-algorithmic-bias-module/</guid>
      <description>Avoiding Algorithmic Bias Module
Module Summary
Ethics background required: Ideally, students should be familiar with the 4 ethical frameworks presented in the first year curriculum (virtue ethics, deontology, utilitarianism, analogies). If they (or the professor) are not, a brief summary is provided in the reflection.
Subject matter referred to in this module: Algorithms
Placement in overall ethics curriculum:
 Academic year: Year 2-4 core course that talks about algorithms or machine learning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computer Addiction Module</title>
      <link>/lab/computer-addiction-module-working-group/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/computer-addiction-module-working-group/</guid>
      <description>Computer Addiction Module
Module Summary
 Ethics background required: Familiarity with the virtue ethics, deontological, and utilitarian ethical frameworks would be helpful. They are briefly reviewed for those who need the information
Subject matter referred to in this module:
Placement in overall ethics curriculum:
 Academic year: Junior or Senior courses. Good candidate for course that covers software engineering.
  Recommended previous modules: First year curriculum
 Recommended follow-up modules: Nothing specific</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Core Values Module</title>
      <link>/lab/core-values-module-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/core-values-module-update/</guid>
      <description>Core Values Module
Module Summary
Ethics background required: None
 This module is designed to help students identify their values and how choices may reflect those values.
 Subject matter referred to in this module: None
Placement in overall ethics curriculum:
Academic year: First semester of first year. Good first semester module.
Recommended previous modules: Why Ethics? Module
Recommended follow-up modules: Virtue Ethics with Coding Scenarios Module
Time required:
Out of class: None (but potential online version available if unable to do in class)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Cleaning Ethics Module</title>
      <link>/lab/data-cleaning-ethics-module/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/data-cleaning-ethics-module/</guid>
      <description>Data Cleaning Ethics Module
For Instructors Module Summary  Main Point: Choices made in data cleaning have ethical implications.
Contents: instructor guide, student handout, suggested assessment questions
Ethics background required: It is helpful if students have learned about the virtue ethics and utilitarian frameworks for making ethical decisions though not absolutely required. These frameworks are covered in the first year curriculum.
Subject matter referred to in this module: Data Cleaning, simple statistics</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ethics in E-Commerce: Digital Nudging</title>
      <link>/lab/e-commerce-with-digital-nudging-module/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/e-commerce-with-digital-nudging-module/</guid>
      <description>Ethics in E-Commerce: Digital Nudging
Module Summary
Ethics background required: This module refers to the following ethics frameworks: Virtue Ethics, Deontology, and Utilitarianism. Brief descriptions of each are included in the take-home assignments so professors and students who are not familiar with these approaches can still complete the module. Using these frameworks reinforces what students learned in the first year curriculum (if that was used).
Subject matter referred to in this module: E-Commerce, Databases, Dark Patterns</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hospitality Module</title>
      <link>/lab/hospitable-code-module/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/hospitable-code-module/</guid>
      <description>Hospitality Module
Module Summary
Ethics background desired: Virtue Ethics, Analogies, Utilitarianism, &amp;amp; Deontology. If students or professor are not familiar with these frameworks, a brief summary is provided in the reflection.
Subject matter referred to in this module: Hospitable computer programming (Exercise written in C++ (uses pointers and vectors), and also Java). Could be adapted to another language if preferable.
Placement in overall ethics curriculum:
 Academic year: Years 2-4. To reinforce the need for good programming techniques we recommend using it earlier rather than later!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to the Deontology Framework Using AI</title>
      <link>/lab/deontology/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/deontology/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to the Deontology Framework Using AI
Module Summary
 Ethics background required: Familiarity with Virtue Ethics and the need for the study of ethics in computer and data sciences is helpful
Subject matter referred to in this module: algorithms, artificial intelligence, computer programming
Placement in overall ethics curriculum:
 Academic year: First year, second semester, probably second semester programming course
 Recommended previous modules: Why Ethics? and Virtue Ethics</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Media Literacy Module</title>
      <link>/lab/media-literacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/media-literacy/</guid>
      <description>Media Literacy Module
Module Summary
 Ethics background required: Basic understanding of the analogy ethical framework is helpful, but it will be briefly reviewed in the module.
Subject matter referred to in this module:
This module can be used as a precursor to any assignment where students are required to perform research on the web and are expected to choose their own articles. References are made to technology, but no specific knowledge is needed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Source Accessibility Module</title>
      <link>/lab/open-source-accessibility-module/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/open-source-accessibility-module/</guid>
      <description>Open Source Accessibility Module
Module Summary
 Ethics background required: It is helpful if students are familiar with the utilitarian and virtue ethics methods of considering ethical dilemmas. They should understand what stakeholders are. For any who need it, there are brief reviews of these concepts in the assignment. It is suggested that the Media Literacy module be completed prior to this module, but principles of finding credible articles is reviewed in the student homework handout.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Professional ethics</title>
      <link>/lab/professional-ethics-module/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/professional-ethics-module/</guid>
      <description>Professional ethics
Module Summary
Ethics background required: Ideally, students should be familiar with the four ethical frameworks presented in the first year curriculum (virtue ethics, deontology, utilitarianism, analogies). If they (or the professor) are not, brief summaries are provided in the activity section.
Subject matter referred to in this module: Professional Ethics
Placement in overall ethics curriculum:
 Academic year: Year 2-4 core course that talks about professional ethics.
 Recommended previous modules: First year ethics curriculum</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reliability Module</title>
      <link>/lab/code-reliability-module/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/code-reliability-module/</guid>
      <description>Reliability Module
Module Summary
 Ethics background required: Familiarity with the virtue ethics, deontological, and utilitarian ethical frameworks would be helpful. They are briefly reviewed for those who need the information
Subject matter referred to in this module: computer programming, testing, documentation, code structure, user training
Placement in overall ethics curriculum:
 Academic year: Junior or Senior courses. Good candidate for course that covers professionalism,
software engineering. Students should have had experience with larger projects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transparency Module</title>
      <link>/lab/transparency-module/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/transparency-module/</guid>
      <description>Transparency Module
Module Summary
 Ethics background required: Basic understanding of virtue ethics, analogy, utilitarian, and deontological ethical frameworks is helpful, but they will be briefly reviewed in the module.
Subject matter referred to in this module: Software, e-commerce, and/or social media user agreements.
Placement in overall ethics curriculum:
 Academic year: Years 2-4 Software Engineering or other Software design course
  Recommended previous modules: Year one curriculum covering ethical frameworks is helpful.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Virtue Ethics</title>
      <link>/lab/virtue-ethics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/virtue-ethics/</guid>
      <description>Virtue Ethics
Overview  Ethics background required: None
Subject matter referred to in this module: Computer Programming
Placement in overall ethics curriculum:
 Academic year: First year, first semester, probably introductory programming course
 Recommended previous modules: A First Look at Ethics in Computer and Data Science
 Recommended follow-up modules: Analogies* *
Time required:
 Out of class: None
  In class: 20-30 minutes
Learning objectives:
  Students further understand how the virtue ethics framework works</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Ethics? Module</title>
      <link>/lab/why-ethics-module-revised/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/why-ethics-module-revised/</guid>
      <description>Why Ethics? Module
Module Summary
 Ethics background required: None. This module motivates the need for ethics education in computer science and/or data science.
Subject matter referred to in this module: What do computer scientists/data scientists do?
Placement in overall ethics curriculum:
 Academic year: First module in the first year of curriculum use. Ideally, this is the first semester of the freshman year. We would recommend that the students are 3-4 weeks into the first semester when this module is administered.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
